Good morning, today is Monday, 11th of אדר, Adar, it's March 21st,
and I'm Dan Margulies filling in for Ephraim Lindzer while he's away.
Hopefully, he'll be back tomorrow. I think that's the plan. And we
are going to pick up toward the bottom of ט' עמוד ב'.
Tet Amud Bet. The discussion had been about a case of determining
under what circumstances is a woman who is raped by a number
of men, which of them are treated as perpetrators of the violation
נערה מאורסה, Na'arah Me'orasah, that is raping a woman who had been
married but was a virgin, that is she had been there was
קידושין Kiddushin already but she's a virgin, compared to a case of
an adulterous kind of rape where the punishments are different. In the
case of נערה מאורסה, Na'arah Me'orasah, the punishment is by סקילה, Skilah,
but in the case of any sort of adultery, the punishment is
with חנק, Chenek, which is a less severe kind of death penalty.
Great, sounds they both sound pretty bad.
They you end up dead either way, but the חז"ל Chazal at
least have an understanding that סקילה Skilah is somehow worse than חנק.
Chenek. It's interesting to think about just the fact that there are
different kinds of death penalties and each of them has different qualities
and different characteristics in a variety of ways. Part of that evaluation
centers around how damaging they are to the human body. Interestingly enough,
the whole discussion in סנהדרין Sanhedrin is about ואהבת לרעך כמוך, V'ahavta
L'reiacha Kamocha,
always creeps in in interesting סוגיות, Sugyos, so ואהבת לרעך כמוך V'ahavta
L'reiacha Kamocha is ברור לו מיתה יפה. Bror Lo Misah Yafah. You
have to pick an appropriate or pleasant sort of death for someone
even when you execute them. So that, yeah.
So if she didn't participate willingly, she still receives—
No, no, she she doesn't get the— this is a case of
rape. The woman is innocent. And the question then is how the
rapist, or in this case multiple rapists, would be punished.
So the ברייתא Braita had said באו עליה עשרה אנשים ועדיין היא
בתולה. Bao Aleha Asarah Anashim V'adain Hi Besulah. There could be ten
men who rape the same woman and she's still considered a בתולה,
Besulah, that is that all ten of them would receive סקילה Skilah
for that act because it's referring to anal sex, which would not
have the same consequences as vaginal sex in that she's still considered
to be a בתולה Besulah afterwards. And this is a debate between
רבי Rebbi and רבנן. Rabbanan. So we pick up from about eight
lines up from the bottom from the קא משמע לן Kamashma Lan
ורבי האי סברא מנא ליה. V'Rebbi Hai Svara Menaleh. So how does
רבי Rebbi have this opinion? אם כן לכתוב רחמנא ובעל. Im Ken
Lichtov Rachmana U'baal. The פסוק Pasuk could have just said ובעל. U'baal.
In fact, that the פסוק Pasuk referring to marriage says ובעלה. U'be'alah.
מאי ובעלה? Mai U'be'alah? שמע מינה תרתי. Shema Mina Tartei. רבי Rebbi
can learn two things from that word because he can learn the
word says ובעל U'baal and the extra ה Heh for a דרשה.
Drasha. ולרבא דאמר בר אהני אסיברא לי כי יקח איש אשה ובעלה.
U'l'Rava D'amar Bar Ahannai Asivra Li Ki Yikach Ish Ishah U've'alah. קידושין
המסורין לביאה הוי קידושין. Kiddushin Hamesurin L'viah Havei Kiddushin. So
רבא Rava later uses that פסוק Pasuk to learn the principle קידושין
המסורין לביאה הוי
קידושין—that Kiddushin Hamesurin L'viah Havei Kiddushin קידושין Kiddushin for which a sexual
relationship would be permitted afterwards counts as קידושין. Kiddushin. But קידושין שאין
מסורין לביאה Kiddushin She'ein Mesurin L'viah. לא הוי havei,
קידושין—קידושין which at the time of קידושין Kiddushin perhaps the sexual relationship
would be prohibited are not קידושין. Kiddushin So רבא Rava uses that
for that דרשה. Drasha. Turn ahead to דף נ"א Daf Nun Aleph
if you have it. On דף נ"א עמוד א', Daf Nun Aleph
Amud Aleph, there's a מחלוקת Machlokes between רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot
how to understand the principle of קידושין שאין מסורין לביאה. Kiddushin She'ein
Mesurin L'viah רש"י's Rashi principle is that it refers to any and
all of the עריות, Arayos, that is prohibited sexual relationships. Obviously those
if you would try to marry your sister or you would try
to marry your brother, you try to marry your grandmother, you try
to marry your grandfather, those sorts of relationships would not work because
they're ערוה. Ervah. And תוספות Tosafot is upset because
I actually see your problem.
Fine, okay, so that's part of the question. Meaning, but we know
that there is a principle that certain kinds of עריות Arayos at
least the relationship is categorized as אין קידושין תופסין, Ein Kiddushin Tofsin,
that the קידושין Kiddushin. do not even take effect. According to at
least some of the תנאים, Tannaim, that's the qualification for what makes
a ממזר Mamzer is if it's the relationship where the ערוה Ervah
is so severe that קידושין Kiddushin would not even work. But תוספות
Tosafot disagrees and תוספות Tosafot thinks קידושין שאין מסורין לביאה Kiddushin She'ein
Mesurin L'viah actually doesn't refer to ערוה Ervah at all. And תוספות
Tosafot thinks it's referring to the relationship the difference between two different
kinds of relationships that are prohibited in הלכה. Halachah. There are חייבי
לאוין, Chayvei Lavin, that is a כהן Kohen marrying a זונה Zonah
or a ישראל Yisrael marrying a ממזרת Mamzeret or something like that.
Those relationships, חייבי לאוין, Chayvei Lavin, those are unaffected by a marital
status, that is the prohibition is—I'm sorry, the opposite. The prohibition is
to become married. So the same prohibition existed
before and—I'm sorry, I got mixed up a little bit.
Right. So that תוספות Tosafot says התקדשי לי בקידושין לכך נראה לפרש
קידושין שאין מסורין לביאה כלומר שאיסור הביאה על ידי קידושין. Hatkadshi Li
B'kiddushin L'kach Nireh Lefarish Kiddushin She'ein Mesurin L'viah Klomar She'issur Habiah Al
Yedei Kiddushin. תוספות Tosafot think that קידושין Kiddushin שאין מסורין לביאה means
it refers to a case where the איסור ביאה— Issur Biah kicks
in because of marriage. That is a relative who you marry into.
For example, the case on נ"א Nun Alef is a man tries
to marry one of two sisters, but he does not make clear
which of the two sisters he married. So then there's a prohibition
of being married to your wife's sister, and then now he's stuck.
Neither of them is permitted to him because of the ספק. sofek.
So that's the case that תוספות Tosfos thinks that קידושין שאינם מסורים
לביאה Kiddushin she'einam mesurim l'viah is talking about. And the ר"ן Ran
on דף א' Daf Alef in דפי הרי"ף Dafei HaRif in כתובות
Kesuvos asks a קשיא kasha from the first משנה Mishna in מסכת
יומא, Maseches Yoma, which is that we prepare a spare wife for
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol in case his wife dies on יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. But because the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur has to be married. But the question is, so
then you can't get married on יום כיפור Yom Kippur because it
would be קידושין שאינם מסורים לביאה. Kiddushin she'einam mesurim l'viah. You cannot
have sex on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and therefore they would not
be real קידושין, Kiddushin, and the ר"ן Ran has to deal with
that. So that's an interesting question.
We could have אירוסין erusin but I don't think that—No,
this אירוסין erusin is קידושין. Kiddushin. קידושין Kiddushin has to be ראויים
לביאה. reuyim l'viah. It has to be נמסרים לביאה. nimsorim l'viah. That
is, you are not allowed to have sex right after קידושין, Kiddushin,
but you are only allowed to have קידושין Kiddushin with someone with
whom you will later be allowed to have sex. That's what that
principle means.
You could have מוצאי יום motzoei Yom on the 11th of תשרי.
Tishrei.
So that has to be part of the ר"ן'ס Ran's answer, but
it's an interesting question at least. Okay, so that's רבא. Rava. רבא
דאמר בר אהני סבר לה כהכי, Rava d'amar Bar Ahani savar lei
k'hakhi, קי יקח אשה ובעלה קידושין המסורים לביאה הוי קידושין קידושין שאינם
מסורים לביאה לא הוי קידושין. ki yikach ish isha u'va'alah Kiddushin hamisurim
l'viah havei Kiddushin Kiddushin she'einam misurim l'viah lo havei Kiddushin. מאי איכא
למימר? Mai ika l'meimar? אם כן נכתוב קרא או בעלה. Im kein
nichtov kra o ba'alah. So even we could learn רבא'ס Rava's שיטה
shita even for רבי. Rebbi. That is, it could have said או
בעלה. o ba'alah. כי יקח איש אשה או בעלה, Ki yikach ish
isha o ba'alah, either take קידושין Kiddushin or have a sexual relationship.
So the fact it says ובעלה, u'va'alah, it says u-both, שמע מינה
כולהו. shma mina kulu hu. רבי, Rebbi, האי בעולת בעל מאי עביד
ליה? hai Be'ulas Ba'al mai avid lei? So what does רבי Rebbi
then do with the פסוק pasuk בעולת בעל? Be'ulas Ba'al? Because we
said that רבי Rebbi learns all of these from the פסוק pasuk
ובעלה, u'va'alah, and the רבנן Rabbanan use another פסוק pasuk to learn
קידושי ביאה, Kiddushei Biah, that is בעולת בעל. Be'ulas Ba'al. So what
does רבי Rebbi learn from the פסוק pasuk בעולת בעל, Be'ulas Ba'al,
the פסוק pasuk by נערה המאורסה? Naarah HaMeorasah? So רבי Rebbi learns,
מאי עביד
ליה? mai avid lei? האי מבעי ליה בעל עושה אותה בעולה שלא
כדרכה ואין אחר עושה אותה בעולה שלא כדרכה. Hai mibaei lei ba'al
osah b'ula shelo k'darkah ve'ein acher oseh b'ula shelo k'darkah. That is,
that a woman who has anal sex with her husband, that counts
as sex to make her not a בתולה, besulah, but if a
woman were to be anally raped by another man, that would not
make her to be considered a בעולה beulah and therefore she would
still—the rapist would be punished by סקילה skilah rather than חנק. chenek.
ומאי אית ליה לרבי האי סברא בהא דתניא באו עליה עשרה אנשים
ועדיין היא בתולה כולם בסקילה רבי אומר אומר אני הראשון בסקילה וכולם
בחנק. U'mai it lei le'Rebbi hai savra b'ha d'tanya ba'u alehah asarah
anashim ve'adayin hi besulah kulum b'skilah Rebbi omer omer ani harishon b'skilah
ve'kulum b'chenek. So what does רבי Rebbi do with the ברייתא? brayisa?
רבי Rebbi adds on his own line at the end where he
disagrees with the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. So the תנא קמא'ס Tanna
Kamma's position is along with the רבנן Rabbanan and רבי Rebbi says,
אומר אני הראשון בסקילה, omer ani harishon b'skilah, only the first one
is punished by סקילה skilah because he's the husband who married her
by קידושי ביאה Kiddushei Biah and the rest are by חנק. chenek.
Okay, just to note an interesting point, the only תנא, Tanna, at
least as far as I know, who ever says אומר אני omer
ani is רבי. Rebbi. So some of the אחרונים acharonim have pointed
out that's sort of like נראה לעניות דעתי nireh la'aniyus da'ati in
the אחרוניש acharonish parlance, that is a certain kind of humility. רבי
Rebbi doesn't present his own—even though he's the author of the משנה,
Mishna, he doesn't present his own שיטות shitos as being more important
than anyone else's, he actually kind of has a certain humility. We
saw at the end of סוטה Sotah that רבי Rebbi had a
very high level of humility. So that's one aspect of that.
Okay, אמר רבי זירא מודה רבי לעניין קנס דכולהו משלמי. Amar Rabbi
Zeira modeh Rebbi l'inyan knas d'kulu m'shalmi. No, so according to רבי
זירא, Rabbi Zeira, רבי Rebbi agrees with the רבנן Rabbanan that all
ten rapists would pay the 50 shekel קנס. knas. The מחלוקת machlokes
is only about what death penalty they get, whether they get חנק
chenek or whether they get סקילה. skilah. So מודה רבי לעניין קנס
דכולהו משלמי. modeh Rebbi l'inyan knas d'kulu m'shalmi. מאי שנא מקטלא? Mai
shna miketala? What's the difference between paying the fine and being executed?
שאני התם דאמר קרא ומת האיש אשר שכב עמה לבדו. Shani hasam
d'amar kra u'meis ha'ish asher shachav imah l'vado. The man who slept
with her is the only one who will die. That's in the
case of rape obviously because the woman is innocent in the case
of rape, so she will not be executed as opposed to a
case where a woman who was already married had a willing consensual
adulterous relationship in which case she would also be executed. ורבנן האי
לבדו מאי עביד ליה? Ve'Rabbanan hai l'vado mai avid lei? So what
do the רבנן Rabbanan then do with the word לבדו? l'vado? The
word לבדו l'vado to exclude the other nine rapists, that's for רבי'ס
Rebbi's שיטה. shita. So
what do the רבנן Rabbanan use that
word for? מאי עביד ליה מבעי להו לכדתניא ומתו גם שניהם עד
שיהיו שווים כאחד, Mai avid lei mibaei lehu l'khid'tanya u'meisu gam shneihem
ad she'yehu shavin k'echad, דברי רבי יאשיה. divrei Rabbi Yoshiyah. רבי יונתן
Rabbi Yonasan אומר, omer, ומת האיש אשר שכב עמה לבדו, u'meis ha'ish
asher shachav imah l'vado, he דרש darshens it differently. He says the
פסוק pasuk says ומת האיש אשר שכב עמה לבדו, u'meis ha'ish asher
shachav imah l'vado, the man who slept with her himself will die.
ורבי האי סברא מנא ליה? Ve'Rebbi hai savra minalei? אם כן נכתוב
קרא בעולת איש מאי בעולת בעל שמע מינה תרתי. Im kein nichtov
kra Be'ulas Ish mai Be'ulas Ba'al shma mina tartei. within רבי'ס Rebbi's
position that you don't, that you use this to learn all these
הלכות halachot about נערה המאורסה, na'arah ha'me'urasah, nonetheless, you could still manage
to fit everything into the דרשות. drashas. We'll pick up on י',
Yud, י' עמוד א' Yud amud aleph at the two dots. איבעיא
להו, ibayah lehu, תחלת ביאה קונה או סוף ביאה קונה? techilat biah
konah o sof biah konah? Does the initial penetration of a sexual
act work for קנין קידושין, kinyan kiddushin, that is for קידושי ביאה,
kiddushei biah, או סוף ביאה קונה? o sof biah konah? Presumably referring
to ejaculation. נפקא מינה nafka mina כגון שהערה בה ופירש גראדא וקיבלה
kegon sheherah bah uparash grada vekiblah קידושין מאחר. kiddushin meaher. What if
the first man penetrated her but did not complete the sexual act
and then stopped and they separated and she went and received קידושין
kiddushin from someone else somewhere else? So in that case, then the
נפקא מינה, nafka mina, the question is which which part of the
sexual act creates the קנין קידושין. kinyan kiddushin. תוספות Tosfos here brings
four different answers how to resolve this גמרא Gemara with a גמרא
Gemara in יבמות Yevamos that talks about the fact that it's obvious
that by everywhere else, we know that the initial penetration is what
counts for any kind of sexual violation or sexual act in general.
And so תוספות Tosfos here, just some of them to know, I
mean it's important to see, the רשב"א, Rashba, the ריב"ם, Rivam, and
רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, and רבינו נסים גאון, Rabbeinu Nissim Gaon, each
have their own answers, that's תוספות כל הבועל דעתו על גמרא ביאה,
Tosfos kol haboal da'ato al Gemara biah, so each of them has
a very different approach to how do we understand the different processes
involved in a sexual act and it's important תוספות Tosfos to take
a look at later. Okay, so that's a נפקא מינה. nafka mina.
או אינמי o inami לכהן גדול דקקני בתולה בביאה. lekohen gadol dekakaney
betulah beviah. Or if a כהן גדול kohen gadol is trying to
marry his wife through קידושי ביאה. kiddushei biah. That is a כהן
גדול kohen gadol has a מצות עשה mitzvas aseh to marry a
בתולה, betulah, but if the beginning act of sex makes her בעולה,
beulah, we know that from יבמות, Yevamos, but if he's only create
the קנין קידושין kinyan kiddushin at the end, then it would never
be permitted for a כהן גדול kohen gadol to marry his wife
with קידושי ביאה. kiddushei biah. We're going to find out later that
already in the time of אמוראים Amoraim it became forbidden for anyone
to use קידושי ביאה, kiddushei biah, but it's important to consider this
aspect for the כהן גדול. kohen gadol. מאי אמר אמימר? mai amar
Amemar? אמר משמיה דרבא amar mashmei deRabba כל הבועל דעתו על גמר
ביאה. kol haboal da'ato al gmar biah. So according to אמימר, Amemar,
quoting from רבא, Rabba, whoever has sex is intent is only to
wait until the completion of the sexual act, and that's an important
חזקה chazakah here. Obviously, that's the point that contradicts with the גמרא
Gemara in יבמות Yevamos that תוספות Tosfos has to reconcile.
It's weird in what sense?
Well, that it's an interesting discussion at least. Obviously the question is
we're trying to essentialize the act involved. Obviously considering the fact that
we're talking here about using an act of sex as a קנין
kinyan for קידושין, kiddushin, what creates that legal status and maybe be
different than sort of a colloquial or common sense of what is
or is not a sexual act. איבעיא להו ביאה נישואין עושה או
אירוסין עושה? ibayah lehu biah nisuin oseh o eirusin oseh? This is
an important question. Is קידושי ביאה kiddushei biah actually different than other
the other two modes of קידושין? kiddushin? We know that with קידושי
כסף kiddushei kessef and קידושי שטר, kiddushei shtar, you give the כסף
kessef or you give the שטר, shtar, and that's קידושין. kiddushin. And
then you need a second process called חופה chuppah that creates the
נישואין. nisuin. So here we see, איבעיא להו ביאה נישואין עושה או
אירוסין עושה? ibayah lehu biah nisuin oseh o eirusin oseh? Does one
act of ביאה biah actually do both steps together? Could a single
act of קידושי ביאה kiddushei biah reach the stage of נישואין nisuin
already automatically? נפקא מינה ליורשה ולהטמא לה ולהפר נדריה. nafka mina leyorshah
uletamei lah ulehafer nedareiah. These are three things that are influenced by
whether or not it was קידושין kiddushin or not. That is for
inheritance purposes, if the husband only inherits his wife's property if she
would die after נישואין. nisuin. Or ולהטמא לה uletamei lah if he's
a כהן, kohen, then he can only become טמא tamei to be
involved in her funeral and burial process if they are at the
stage of נישואין. nisuin. או ולהפר נדריה o ulehafer nedareiah to nullify
her vows, that is also only the the husband's lone right if
she if she is נשואה. nisuah. But during אירוסין eirusin it's a
combined strength of the father and the husband together. We learn that
in מסכת נדה Masechet Niddah towards the middle. אם אמרת נישואין עושה
יורשה ומטמא לה ומיפר נדריה. im amart nisuin oseh yorshah umitamei lah
umafer nedareiah. If it was נישואין nisuin then he is able to
do all of those things. אם אמרת אירוסין עושה אינו יורשה ואינו
מטמא לה ואינו מיפר נדריה. im amart eirusin oseh eino yorsha ve'eino
mitamei lah ve'eino meifar nedareiah. And if it was only אירוסין eirusin
then it would not work. It's very interesting the גמרא Gemara spells
it all out for
us. מאי אמר אביי? mai amar Abaye? תא שמע, tashma, האב זכאי
בבתו בקידושיה בכסף בשטר ובביאה ha'av zakai bevito bekiddusheha bechessef bishtar ubeviah
וזכאי במציאתה ובמעשה ידיה ובהפרת נדריה מקבל גיטה ואינו אוכל פירות בחייה
נישאת יתר עליו הבעל שאוכל פירות בחייה.
vezakai bemetziatah uvimaseh yadeha ubehafaras nedareiah mekabel gitteha ve'eino
ochel peirot bechayyeiah nisseit yeter alav habaal she'ochel peirot bechayyeiah. So אביי
Abaye quotes now from a ברייתא beraita and he says the father
has the rights to his daughter's קידושין kiddushin for כסף, kessef, שטר,
shtar, and ביאה, biah, strange that it talks about קידושי ביאה kiddushei
biah because it's unclear what rights the father has, probably just a
formulaic quote of the three modes of קידושין, kiddushin, וזכאי במציאתה vezakai
bemetziatah he gets her if she finds a lost object it belongs
to him, ובמעשה ידיה uvimaseh yadeha or if she makes something then
it belongs to the father, you bring home your paycheck from your
summer job so your parents get it, ובהפרת נדריה... ubehafaras nedareiah... The
father has the power to annul her vows. ובקבלת גיטה, Ubekabalat gitah,
he can receive her גט get for her. ואינו אוכל פירות בחייה,
Ve’eino ochel peirot bechayyeha, and he is not allowed to while she
owns property that she bought under her own name, he does not
get the produce from those properties in her lifetime. ניסת, Nisset, if
she marries, that is, once she marries her husband, יתר עליו הבעל,
Yeter alav habaal, the בעל baal has more rights than the father,
שאוכל פירות בחייה. She'ochel peirot bechayyeha. The husband has rights to the
produce of the wife's uniquely owned property. That is when a woman
brings real estate into a marriage, the husband has certain rights to
the produce of that real estate during the marriage. קתני ביאה וקתני
ניסת. Katani biah vekatani nisset. It says ביאה biah and it says
ניסת nisset as two different stages. That is the first stage mentioned
קידושי ביאה, Kiddushei biah, and then it said יתר עליו הבעל Yeter
alav habaal in a case of ניסת. nisset. So therefore כל קתני
ניסת אשארא. Kol katani nisset ashara. So they have to deflect that
and say even למאן דאמר le'man de'amar if you would want to
say the one position who holds
that ביאה biah is נישואין עושה, nissuin oseh, nonetheless you could say
ניסת nisset just refers to if you had done קידושי כסף Kiddushei
kessef or קידושי שטר, Kiddushei shtar, but קידושי ביאה Kiddushei biah obviously
would reach the stage of נישואין nissuin anyway. Or it fits obviously
as a better fit for the opinion who says ביאה biah does
not do נישואין. nissuin. אמר רבא תא שמע. Amar Rava ta shema.
So רבא Rava now brings another ברייתא. braita. בת שלש שנים ויום
אחד מתקדשת בביאה. Bat shalosh shanim veyom echad mitkadeshet bebiah. Once a
girl reaches the age of three, we know this general הלכתית halachic
principle, just as you have to pick an arbitrary cutoff, חז"ל Chazal
happened to pick what to us seems to be a very young
age as an arbitrary cutoff, but the age of three is the
age at which a woman's sexual act counts as sex. If you
look in רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says younger than
that, אבל פחות מכאן כנותן אצבע בעין. Aval pachot mikan kenoten etzba
ba'ayin. Lower than the age of three is like putting a finger
in the eye. That is to say that it's not even sex.
Obviously this touches on important questions about child abuse and how to
הלכתית halachically address issues about child abuse from a variety of angles,
and תוספות Tosafot deals with that to a certain extent here as
well. Interesting to note that it's not uniquely a modern problem. So
תא שמע בת שלש שנים ויום אחד מתקדשת בביאה. Ta shema bat
shalosh shanim veyom echad mitkadeshet bebiah. From the age of three a
girl could be מתקדשת בביאה. mitkadeshet bebiah. ואם בא עליה יבם קנאה,
Ve'im ba aleha yavam kna'ah, or if her brother-in-law, that is she
had already been married, her husband had died, obviously they have no
children because she was from the age of three, then the יבם
yavam can have sex with her to perform יבום yibbum וחייבים עליה
משום אשת איש, Vechayavim aleha mishum eshet ish, and anyone who would
sleep with her after she is married violates the prohibition on אשת
איש eshet ish adultery. ומטמאה בועלה לטמא משכב תחתון כעליון, Ummetama bo'alah
letame mishkav tachton ke'elyon, and whoever has sex with her while she
is נידה niddah is made to be—yes, sorry, I'm just—No, I
was just saying how she can be a נידה? niddah?
Well, how could she be a נידה? niddah? There are various hormonal
situations in which even infant girls can have some kind of vaginal
bleeding. It's not exactly the same thing as menstruation or it's referring
to someone who's below the age—right, the
age of puberty has plummeted over the last—and it's gone up and
down over the course of history. Right.
Important point about בועל נידה. bo'el niddah. So the תורה Torah prescribes
the fact that טומאה tumah of נידה niddah is transferred to a
person who has sex with a woman while she's in נידה. niddah.
That is that there is a prohibition on having sex during נידה,
niddah, but also the טומאה tumah transfers in a way. But it's
not an equivalent transfer. The man called a בועל נידה, bo'el niddah,
he is an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, but he's only מטמא. metame.
So it says מטמאה לטמא משכב תחתון כעליון. Metame letame mishkav tachton
ke'elyon. A person who has some kind of a bodily flow, that
is a זב, zav, זבה, zavah, יולדת, yoledet, or a נידה, niddah,
sits on even a million couches—you imagine Princess and the Pea—sits on
the top, all of them are considered משכב הזב mishkav hazav or
משכב הנידה mishkav haniddah or whatever. That טומאה tumah transfers to all
of them, and they could transfer even לטמא אדם וכלים. letame adam
vechelim. But if the man who was בועל נידה bo'el niddah sits
on something, it's only like
משכב עליון. mishkav elyon. That is to say that it's like transferred
by contact rather than transferred by this very expansive notion of sitting
on something and it transfers through all of the mattresses. So that's
discussed extensively throughout סדר טהרות. Seder Taharot. It's important just to think
about different ways that טומאה tumah can transfer. And usually when טומאה
tumah transfers, it goes down a level. That is אב הטומאה av
hatumah touches something, becomes ראשון לטומאה, rishon letumah, and it goes down.
But in this case, a נידה niddah with the man she sleeps
with, he also becomes an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. And if she
sits on something, she can make things אב הטומאה. av hatumah. He
sits on something, it doesn't become אב הטומאה, av hatumah, it only
becomes a ולד הטומאה. vlad hatumah. So that's just an important distinction
about some of those different transfers. Some of them transfer actually sort
of a horizontal transfer as well. ואם ניסת לכהן תאכל בתרומה, Ve'im
nisset le'kohen tochal biterumah, if she marries a כהן kohen to the
stage of נישואין, nissuin, she could eat תרומה. terumah. ואם בא עליה
אחד מכל עריות שבתורה מומתים על ידה, Ve'im ba aleha echad mikol
arayot shebatorah mumatim al yadah, if an adult... man who is ערווה
erva to her would have sex with this even a young girl
then he would be executed for violation of prohibition of ערווה. erva.
והיא פטורה vehi petura and obviously as a minor she would be
exempt from any punishment for that. אם בעלה אחד מן הפסולים פסולה
מן הכהונה im ba'ala echad min hapsulim pesula min hakehuna or if
she has sex with someone who makes her such that she cannot
marry a כהן kohein then she would not that that would take
effect. קתני ביאה וקתני ניסת katani bia vekatani nises so so too
this ברייתא braisa also refers to first the stage of ביאה bia
and then separately the stage of ניסת. nises.
So sorry you're saying she wouldn't then be able to marry a
כהן. kohein.
Correct that is after the age of three the act of sex
counts as an act of sex so since she was נבעלה לפסול
nivala lapasul that works to prevent her from being married able to
marry a כהן kohein in the future. Okay so קתני ביאה וקתני
ניסת katani bia vekatani nises this ברייתא braisa also references two different
stages a stage of ביאה bia and a stage of ניסת nises
so that sounds like again a same proof as אביי Abaye had
and רבא Rava also has that ביאה bia and נישואין nissuin are
two different stages. הכי קאמר אי הני נישואין דכהן נינהו אוכלת בתרומה.
hachi kamar i hani nissuin dekohein ninhu ocheles bitruma. Or you could
say no they said ניסת לכהן nises lekohein that isn't a different
stage you could even read it saying they're all נישואין nissuin and
if that נישואין nissuin was to a כהן kohein then she could
eat תרומה. truma. In other words reading it to still fit the
position that says ביאה נישואין עושה bia nissuin osa that is we
don't think that this is a proof against that position. So both
אביי Abaye and רבא Rava have brought a ברייתא braisa that distinguishes
seemingly between ביאה bia and ניסת nises and the גמרא gemara finds
a way to deflect that challenge. So we're really trying to defend
that שיטה shita ביאה נישואין עושה bia nissuin osa it seems. Okay
וקתני ניסת קאמר הני נישואין דכהן נינהו אוכלת בתרומה. vekatani nises kamar
hani nissuin dekohein ninhu ocheles bitruma. תא שמע ta shema so now
we have another ברייתא. braisa. וכבר שלח יוחנן בן בג בג אצל
רבי יהודה בן בתירה לנציבין. uchvar shalacha yochanan ben bag bag etzel
rabi yehuda ben beseira lintzivin. So רבי יוחנן בן בג בג rabi
yochanan ben bag bag sent a message to יהודה בן בתירה yehuda
ben beseira in נציבין. nitzivin. שמעתי עליך שאתה אומר ארוסה בת ישראל
אוכלת בתרומה. shamati alecha sheata omer arusa bas yisrael ocheles bitruma. I
heard that you פוסקן pasken that a woman already at the stage
of קידושין kidushin can eat תרומה truma that is a ישראל yisrael
woman married a כהן kohein by קידושין kidushin and you פוסקן pasken
you רבי יהודה בן בתירה rabi yehuda ben beseira you פוסקן pasken
that she could eat תרומה. truma. שלח לו ואתה אי אתה אומר
כן shalach lo veata i ata omer ken you you don't פוסקן
pasken like that. Okay מוחזקני בך שאתה בקי בחדרי תורה לדרוש קל
וחומר. muchzakani becha sheata baki bechadrei tora lidrosh kal vachomer. I thought
you're a big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and you know you're בקי
בחדרי תורה baki bechadrei tora to be able to learn קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. It's interesting to note קל וחומר kal vachomer is based
on logic. So why do you have to be בקי בחדרי תורה?
baki bechadrei tora? You have to be very fluent in all of
the many different areas and details of הלכה halacha in order to
make a קל וחומר kal vachomer if it's based on logic why
can't you just make it up even if you don't know anything.
Well maybe saying that you're limiting you know a lot of different
sources but you can't you don't know logic perhaps or to say
you have to be able to know under which circumstances you would
be allowed to make קל וחומר kal vachomer s
and which
not.
Meaning you have to know the parameters of the system in order
to even apply logic to the system. אי אתה יודע ומה שפחה
כנענית. i ata yodea u'ma shifcha kena'anis. So now he's going to
tell you his קל וחומר kal vachomer for why he thinks it's
allowed so אי אתה יודע i ata yodea
don't you know ומה שפחה כנענית שאין ביאתה מאכילתה בתרומה כספה מאכילתה
בתרומה u'ma shifcha kena'anis she'ein biata ma'achilta bitruma kaspa ma'achilta bitruma a
female עבד כנעני eved kena'ani a female שפחה כנענית shifcha kena'anis the
fact that she would have sex with her slave master which is
prohibited would not allow her to eat תרומה truma but the purchasing
her with money does allow her to eat תרומה. truma. זו שביאתה
מאכילתה בתרומה zu shebiata ma'achilta bitruma a woman married woman who would
be נקנית nikneis by a sexual act that would allow her to
eat תרומה truma אינו דין שכספה מאכילתה בתרומה eino din shekaspa ma'achilta
bitruma so shouldn't כסף קידושין kesef kidushin also work that is by
a שפחה כנענית shifcha kena'anis ביאה bia does not work but כסף
kesef does work so by a married woman a wife if ביאה
bia does work shouldn't כסף kesef also work. אבל מעשה שהרי אמרו
חכמים aval ma'ase sheharei amru chachamim so he says i can't deal
with it because the rabbis that is a מצווה דרבנן mitzva derabbanan
אין ארוסה בת ישראל אוכלת בתרומה עד שתיכנס לחופה ein arusa bas
yisrael ocheles bitruma ad shetikaneis lechupa מדרבנן miderabbanan the rabbis restricted this
and says that an unmarried married woman should not eat תרומה truma
until after נישואין. nissuin. We saw that already a few דפים dafim
ago the fear that she'll share it with her family members we
know that during the stage of קידושין kidushin a married woman is
still living in her parents home presumably so if she would by
fear that she would share the תרומה truma with her ישראל yisrael
family and then they'll come to eat תרומה. truma. Interesting what if
a כהן kohein girl is marrying into a כהן kohein family but
then there's no problem because she could eat תרומה truma either way
either she's a בת כהן bas kohein or she's a אשת כהן
eshes kohein so either way she's safe.
Okay but it's interesting to consider then would there be a דרבנן
derabbanan period where it would still be prohibited for her to eat
תרומה truma from this meaning at what stage does she leave the
status of בת כהן bas kohein once the time of קידושין kidushin
kicks in maybe you'll say she's no longer really considered בת כהן
bas kohein anymore because she's married and the איסור דרבנן issur derabbanan
in the middle so i think i'm not sure about that it's
an interesting question have to take a look at that
you're saying then you're thinking she wouldn't be able to eat תרומה.
truma.
Exactly, during that middle period between קידושין kiddushin *Kiddushin* and נישואין *Nisuin*,
maybe.
No, just because she can eat his תרומה trumah. *Truma*?
It's an interesting question.
Can't eat her father's תרומה trumah? *Truma* or husband's תרומה trumah.
*Truma*? Well, that's a question, I don't know, I'd have to take
a look into that. Maybe it seems unnecessarily strict for no reason.
Okay. דתניא הכי *De-Tanya Hachi*. Okay, אין ארוסה בת ישראל arusa bat
Yisrael, אוכלת בתרומה עד שתיכנס לחופה היכי דמי *Ein Arusa Bat Yisrael
Ochelet Bi'truma Ad She'tikanes L'chuppah Heichi Dami*. So what case are we
talking about? אי בביאה שעל ידי חופה chuppah, וכסף שעל ידי חופה
ובתרווייהו מיכל אכלה *Ee B'via She'al Yedei Chuppah V'khesef She'al Yedei Chuppah
U'vitravaihu Michla Achla*. So now this is Yochanan ben Bag-Bag refuting Rabbi
Yehuda ben Beteira's קל וחומר kal vachomer, *Kal V'chomer*. So he says,
I don't understand, היכי דמי *Heichi Dami*, what case are we talking
about? אי בביאה שעל ידי חופה וכסף שעל ידי חופה ובתרווייהו מיכל
אכלה *Ee B'via She'al Yedei Chuppah V'khesef She'al Yedei Chuppah U'vitravaihu Michla
Achla*. If you're talking about ביאה *Biah* that is a קידושי ביאה
*Kidduhei Biah* accompanied by חופה *Chuppah*
and קידושי כסף *Kidduhei Khesef* accompanied by חופה *Chuppah*, then בתרווייהו מיכל
אכלה *Bitravaihu Michla Achla*, then of course she could eat תרומה trumah
*Truma* because she's נשואה *Nisuah*. That's already two stages of marriage. Okay.
ואלא בביאה שעל ידי חופה וכסף שלא על ידי חופה *V'ela B'via
She'al Yedei Chuppah V'khesef Shelo Al Yedei Chuppah*. Or are you talking
about ביאה *Biah* that was accompanied by חופה *Chuppah* compared to כסף
*Khesef* that was not accompanied by חופה *Chuppah*? הכא תרתי והכא חדא
*Hacha Tarti V'hacha Chada*. But then you're talking about you've already accomplished
two stages of marriage compared to one. So obviously they're different, so
you can't make a קל וחומר kal vachomer, *Kal V'chomer*. אלא לאו
בביאה שלא על ידי חופה וכסף שלא על ידי חופה *Ela Lav
B'via Shelo Al Yedei Chuppah V'khesef Shelo Al Yedei Chuppah*. And so
fine, no, I'm going to explain. ביאה *Biah* that did not have
חופה *Chuppah* and כסף *Khesef* that did not have חופה *Chuppah* and
that therefore this קל וחומר *Kal V'chomer* of Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira
is a support for the notion ביאה נישואין עושה *Biah Nisuin Osa*.
אי אמרת בשלמא נישואין עושה *Ee Amart Bishlama Nisuin Osa*, if you're
going to say that ביאה *Biah* is נישואין עושה *Nisuin Osa*, that
is the act of sex reaches already the second stage of marriage.
משום הכי פשיטא ליה דאלימא ביאה מכסף *Mishum Hachi Peshita Lei D'alima
Biah Mikhesef*. It makes sense because you're saying that ביאה *Biah* is
stronger than כסף *Khesef*. אלא אי אמרת קידושין kiddushin עושה *Ela Ee
Amart Kiddushin Osa*, if you think that ביאה *Biah* only does the
first stage of marriage, that is קידושין kiddushin *Kiddushin*, מאי שנא הכא
דפשיטא ליה ומאי שנא הכא דמיספקא ליה *Mai Shna Hacha D'peshita Lei
U'mai Shna Hacha D'mispaka Lei*? So I don't understand, how can you
then distinguish between oh it's obvious to you that ביאה *Biah*, קידושי
ביאה *Kidduhei Biah* is enough to allow you to eat תרומה trumah.
*Truma* but קידושי כסף *Kidduhei Khesef* would not be even though they
both just reach a stage of קידושין kiddushin *Kiddushin*? How can one
be obvious to learn a קל וחומר *Kal V'chomer* from that one
to learn the other one? That is, how could one be a
doubtful case and one be a sure case if they're both just
קידושין kiddushin *Kiddushin*? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק *Amar Rav Nachman Bar
Yitzchak*, לעולם אימא לך בביאה שעל ידי חופה וכסף שלא על ידי
חופה *L'olam Eima Lach B'via She'al Yedei Chuppah V'khesef Shelo Al Yedei
Chuppah*. No, we're talking about ביאה *Biah* that was accompanied by חופה
*Chuppah* and קידושי כסף *Kidduhei Khesef* that was not accompanied by חופה
*Chuppah*. But now we have to have an answer to the הכא
תרתי והכא חדא *Hacha Tarti V'hacha Chada* objection, which is וכי תימא
הכא תרתי והכא חדא קל וחומר מי אתיא *V'chi Teima Hacha Tarti
V'hacha Chada Kal V'chomer Mi Atia*? So how can you make the
קל וחומר *Kal V'chomer*? והכי שלח ליה *V'hachi Shalach Lei*, and this
is what he sent to him. ומה שפחה כנענית שאין ביאתה מאכילתה
בתרומה *U'ma Shifcha Kna'anit She'ein Biatah Ma'achiltah Bi'truma*, a שפחה כנענית *Shifcha
Kna'anit*, who having sex with her does not allow her to eat
תרומה trumah. *Truma*, אפילו על ידי חופה *Afilu Al Yedei Chuppah*, even
if you did חופה *Chuppah* with her also, כסף מאכילתה בלא חופה
*Khesef Ma'achiltah B'lo Chuppah*, and כסף *Khesef* allows her to eat תרומה
trumah, *Truma* even without חופה *Chuppah*. זו שביאתה מאכילתה בתרומה על ידי
חופה *Zu She'biatah Ma'achiltah Bi'truma Al Yedei Chuppah*, this one, a wife,
who ביאה *Biah* plus חופה *Chuppah* does work, אינו דין שכספה מאכילתה
בתרומה בלא חופה *Eino Din She'khaspah Ma'achiltah Bi'truma B'lo Chuppah*? Then shouldn't
קידושי כסף *Kidduhei Khesef* alone work without it? Now obviously this קל
וחומר *Kal V'chomer* is predicated on the basic assumption that we can
equate the role that כסף *Khesef* has by purchasing a slave and
כסף *Khesef* for כסף קידושין kiddushin *Kessef Kiddushin* and the fact that
we see that it does not work, that is the קל וחומר
*Kal V'chomer* does not work, is the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* way of highlighting
the fact that those are different processes.
But to note as well, ביאה *Biah* does not work by שפחה
כנענית *Shifcha Kna'anit*, it's not a marital relationship. It's a very different
kind of process, a very different kind of קניין *Kinyan*. אבל מעשה
שהרי אמרו חכמים אין ארוסה בת ישראל אוכלת בתרומה עד שתיכנס לחופה
*Aval Ma'ase She'harei Amru Chachamim Ein Arusa Bat Yisrael Ochelet Bi'truma Ad
She'tikanes L'chuppah* משום דעולא ובן בג בג גבי שפחה כנענית *Mishum D'Ulla
U'ben Bag Bag Gabei Shifcha Kna'anit*. Okay. So we've reached the point
now where this whole קל וחומר *Kal V'chomer* discussion has been explained,
that is, Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira's קל וחומר *Kal V'chomer* as initially
presented was challenged. It was restructured in a way that's a very
more contrived kind of קל וחומר *Kal V'chomer*, that is ביאה *Biah*
plus חופה *Chuppah* does not work for a שפחה כנענית *Shifcha Kna'anit*
but כסף *Khesef* does. Ah, so shouldn't ביאה *Biah* plus חופה *Chuppah*
that does work for a wife, shouldn't כסף *Khesef* also work? And
then he said, ah, but מדרבנן Midrabbanan. *M'drabbanan*, כסף קידושין kiddushin *Kessef
Kiddushin* isn't enough to let her eat תרומה terumah, *Truma* anyway because
they were worried that she would share the תרומה terumah *Truma* with
her relatives. And therefore the whole point of this conversation was just
to explain that there is no need to read ביאה נישואין עושה
*Biah Nisuin Osa*. That is, we saw Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira's קל
וחומר *Kal V'chomer* was based on the assumption ביאה נישואין עושה *Biah
Nisuin Osa*, and we were able to explain how it in fact
is not. Okay, so now we've reached the point where we said
משום דעולא ובן בג בג גבי שפחה כנענית *Mishum D'Ulla U'ben Bag
Bag Gabei Shifcha Kna'anit*. So that's what we're talking about. Okay. שפחה
כנענית לא שייר בקניינה *Shifcha Kna'anit Lo Shiyer B'kinyanah*. The difference is
that שפחה כנענית *Shifcha Kna'anit*, all you need is one stage, one
act of קניין *Kinyan* to buy a slave. הכא שייר בקניינה *Hacha
Shiyer B'kinyanah*. But with כסף קידושין *Kessef Kiddushin* there's another stage waiting
to take effect. Marriage is a two-stage process. כסף *Khesef* does the
first stage and the second stage is חופה *Chuppah*. So obviously that's
the difference. That's why כסף *Khesef* plays a very different role in
the two processes, partially because it's a totally different חלות *Chalut* and
part of it. because it's a totally different process, a two-stage process
or one-stage process. רבינא Ravina אמר מדאורייתא mide'oraisa, מיפשט פשיטא ליה דאכלה.
So רבינא Ravina explains differently. רבינא says, מדאורייתא, the הלכה halacha is
that a woman at the stage of קידושין can eat תרומה. terumah.
It's obvious.
ומדרבנן הוא דשלח ליה. Umidrabbanan hu deshalach lei. And he, this, that
means the entire conversation now, this whole question between רבי יוחנן בן
בג בג Rabbi Yochanan ben Bag-Bag asking רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi
Yehuda ben Beteira is not a דאורייתא de'oraisa question. It's a דרבנן
derabbanan question. At what stage can a married woman eat תרומה? מדרבנן.
After the גזירה. gezeira. After the fact that a מקודשת mekudeshet woman
is not allowed to eat תרומה. And what's the question? הוא דשלח
ליה והכא שלח ליה. Hu deshalach lei vehacha shalach lei. This is
what he asked him. שמעתי הלכה שאתה אומר ארוסה בת ישראל אוכלת
בתרומה ולא חיישינן לסימפון. Shamati halacha she'ata omer arusa bat Yisrael ochelet
batrumah velo chayshinan lesimpon. So I heard that you say that an
ארוסה בת ישראל, that is a ישראלית Yisraelite woman who was מקודשת
mekudeshet to a כהן kohen is allowed to eat תרומה and you
do not worry about סימפון. simpon. So what's סימפון? simpon? We're going
to have to explain that in just a second. שלח ליה את
את אומר כן מוחזקני בך שאתה בקי בחדרי תורה לדרוש בקל וחומר
אי אתה יודע מה שפחה כנענית שאין ביאתה מכשירתה בתרומה כספה מכשירתה
בתרומה ולא חיישינן לסימפון זו שביאתה מכשירתה בתרומה אינו דין שכספה מכשירתה
בתרומה ולא ניחוש לסימפון. Shalach lei, ata ata omer kein, muchzakani bach
she'ata baki bechadrei Torah lidrosh b'kal vachomer, i ata yode'a mah shivcha
knaanit she'ein bi'ata machshirta betrumah, kaspa machshirta betrumah velo chashinan lesimpon. Zo
shebi'ata machshirta betrumah, einu din shekaspa machshirta betrumah velo neicheish lesimpon. So
he sends back to him the same קל וחומר, but what's סימפון?
simpon? So סימפון, simpon, if you look in רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi
says, סימפון כל דבר המבטל דבר קרוי סימפון. simpon, kol davar hamevatel
davar karui simpon. Anything which undermines something else in the previous רש"י
Rashi משום סימפון שמא ימצא בה מום ונמצאו קידושי טעות. mishum simpon,
shema yimatzei bah mum venimtzu kiddushei taut. So what happened? Suppose there's
קידושין and the man marries a woman. Great. And now she starts
eating תרומה. And then what? And then they start to live together
and he realizes that she has whatever would qualify as a מום,
mum, we don't have to get into that now, it comes up
later in the מסכת. masechet. So some kind of a מום mum
that the husband was unaware of. So now it was קידושי טעות.
kiddushei taut. The whole purpose of getting married, the husband now retroactively
realized he never really meant to marry this woman for this טעות.
taut. This is such a major flaw in her presumably physical appearance
but the question of psychological and mental aspects of טעות taut are
very much at the forefront of modern עגונה agunah שאלות shailos and
so in that case we say we're not worried about סימפון. simpon.
That is, he says there's no fear that a husband now is
retroactively going to undo the קידושין based on finding this מום mum
that this woman has and therefore she will have retroactively been a
ישראלית Yisraelite eating תרומה. Okay, that's the concern. And we say we
don't worry about that. But now let's see, what kind of סימפון
simpon are we talking about? What kind of מום mum are we
talking
about? Okay. אבל מעשה שהרי אמרו חכמים ארוסה בת ישראל אינה אוכלת
בתרומה עד שתיכנס לחופה משום דעולא בן בג בג סימפון בעבדים לית
ליה. Aval maaseh sheharei amru chachamim arusa bat Yisrael eina ochelet batrumah
ad shetikanes lachuppah mishum de'ula ben Bag-Bag, simpon ba'avadim leit lei.
No,
with עבדים avadim there's no concern about these מומים. mumim. Why? אי
מומים
שבגלוי הוא הא קחזי ליה. Ei mumim shebagaluy hu, hakach chazi lei.
He already saw it. אי משום מומים שבסתר, Ei mishum mumim shebasseter,
or if it was something hidden that's on a covered part of
her body, מאי נפקא ליה מיניה למלאכה קא בעי ליה ולא איכפת
ליה. mai nafka lei minei? Limalacha kaba'ei lei velo ichpat lei. So
the fact is, who cares if she has a מום mum on
a covered part of her body? He bought a slave in order
to have her as a laborer of some kind to work in
the home, to work in the field or something. So it doesn't
matter if she has a physical מום mum on a covered part
of her body because he's not going to see that. So what
about now this important clause: נמצא גנב או קוביוסטוס הגיעו. Nimtza ganav
o kubyustis, hegi'o. What if the slave was found to be a
גנב ganav thief or a קוביוסטוס kubyustis
kidnapper? הגיעו, hegio, it arrived to him, that is, it means he
already knew about it. Why so? מאי קאמרת ליסטין מזויין Mai ka'amart
listim meduyyan? Do we say that it's because robbers are well-known? אי
נכתב למלכות הנה קלא אית להו. Ei nichtav lamalchut hinu kala it
leihu.
If he's already been prosecuted by the government, then there's a קלא,
kol, that is, he's already known to be a criminal. מכדי בין
למר בין למר לא אכלה מאי בינייהו קיבל מסר והלך. Mechdi, bein
lemar bein lemar lo achla mai bainaiyhu? Kibbel, masar, vehalach.
So what about a case where already we're talking about קיבל מסר
והלך? kibbel, masar, vehalach? Those are three different cases. You look in
רש"י, Rashi, קיבל עליו את המומים. kibbel alav et hamumim. So the
first case is what if the husband accepted the מומים? mumim? It
means he knew about it. Okay. מסר, masar, what about מסר? masar?
האב לשלוחי הבעל או שהלכו שלוחי האב עם שלוחי הבעל ועודה בדרך
משום סימפון איכא ומשום שמא תשקה איכא. Ha'av lishluchei habaal o shehalchu
shluchei ha'av im shluchei habaal ve'oda baderech mishum simpon ika umishum shema
tashkeh ika.
The two different reasons for a married woman from the stage of
קידושין not to eat תרומה, the first one because maybe she's going
to share with her relatives, the second one because of סימפון. simpon.
So those are the נפקא מינהס. nafka minas. קיבל, kibbel, if the
husband accepted the מום. mum. The two different reasons for a married
woman from the stage of קידושין not to eat תרומה, the first
one because maybe she's going to share with her relatives, the second
one because of סימפון, simpon, so those are the נפקא מינות. nafka
minas. קיבל, kibel, if the husband accepted the מום, mum, then it's
fine, but it wouldn't solve the problem of maybe she'll share it
with her family. מסר, masar, if the husband has sent her תרומה
food to eat on the way while she's traveling to his house
once she already left her parent's house, well then מום mum is
still a problem, but sharing it with her family's not a problem.
So those two different cases, מסר masar and הלך halach and קיבל,
kibel, are two different cases to test whether we פוסקין poskin one
or the other of those reasons for a married woman from the
time of קידושין not eating תרומה. But nonetheless, the point is that
by עבדים, avadim, we don't say that מום mum is a problem,
a physical מום mum at least. The question is, well what about
a criminal background? And the גמרא Gemara refutes that and says, well,
criminal background is well-known.
Somebody said there's only armed robbery. What about just like petty thievery?
Okay, so גנב. ganav.
Why does it have to be so extreme?
No, גזלן gazlan is armed robbery, right? גנב, ganav, גנב ganav is
a thief, it's a kleptomaniac type. You're not going to have that
person, you don't want such a person.
לסטים מזוין. listim mezuyan.
Right, so that means exactly. So the difference, in other words, that
a גנב, ganav, a regular גנב ganav would still be a problem,
and that's an opening to consider the fact that a psychological or
or behavioral problem in an עבד eved nonetheless that would still be
a מום. mum. That is armed robbery where a case, either a
person who is an armed robber or a person who's been prosecuted
by the government, such is a problem, because but it's already well-known.
No, he says הוי, and therefore this is the whole point was
this, what would, why is בן בג בג Ben Bag Bag objecting
to the קל וחומר, right? He's saying because ממה נפשך, mima nafshach,
no matter what I have my bases covered, but I'm saying it's
not
true because an unarmed, that is a thief, exactly. גנב, ganav, the
question of נמצא גנב, nimtza ganav, right? So look in רש"י. Rashi.
The גנב, ganav, נמצא גנב אינו בטל בכך דהא קיימא לן המוכר
עבד לחברו ונמצא גנב או קוביוסטוס הגיעו. nimtza ganav eino batel bekach
deha kayma lan hamocher eved lachaveiro venimtza ganav o kuvyostos higi'o.
So that's from the ברייתא. Baraisa. And then exactly your question, which
is a גנב ganav is unarmed, so is not a problem. So
we have to say really when it says גנב ganav it was
talking about לסטים מזוין, listim mezuyan, which means that if you're talking
then about unarmed robbery, that is petty thievery, perhaps there is an
opening to consider the fact that even for an עבד eved such
would still be considered a מום, mum, but it certainly you kind
of have to thread the needle with the ברייתא. Baraisa.
Okay, just a few other points. If we turn back to י'
עמוד א', yud amud aleph, there's an interesting מחלוקת machlokes between the
רמב"ם Rambam and the ראב"ד. Ra'avad. The רמב"ם Rambam about this whole
question of the role of anal sex in rape cases. So the
רמב"ם Rambam and the ראב"ד Ra'avad have a מחלוקת, machlokes, and the
רמב"ם Rambam thinks that, sorry, if you take a look at the
תוספות רי"ד הזקן, Tosafot Rid HaZaken, which is not the תוספות רי"ד
הזקן Tosafot Rid HaZaken in the,
it's probably רב אברהם מן ההר Rav Avraham Min HaHar because his
main project in מסכת קידושין Masechet Kiddushin is defending the רמב"ם Rambam
from the רמב"ם's Rambam critics. And we know that that was one
of רב אברהם מן ההר Rav Avraham Min HaHar in the פרובינציאל
חכמים's Provencial Chakhamim general project. So often if you take a look,
there's right in the middle of the line says דהרמב"ם כתב, DehaRambam
katav, so that's the רמב"ם. Rambam. What lines? No, the narrow lines.
About two-thirds of the way down in the narrow lines, דהרמב"ם כתב
בנערה בבתולה
פרק א' שאינו משלם קנס אלא כדרכה. DehaRambam katav bena'arah bivtulah perek
aleph she'eino meshalem knas ela kedarka. So he says in a case
of rape of נערה המאורסה, na'arah hame'orasah, the rapist only pays the
קנס knas if it was vaginal sex, but not anal sex. So
that's the רמב"ם Rambam שיטה shita and the ראב"ד Ra'avad fiercely disagrees
with him
based on this גמרא. Gemara. That is, this גמרא Gemara seems by
the case of rape to fully equate anal and vaginal sex. It's
just an interesting question to consider part of what does the תורה
Torah conceptualize as the crime of rape. Obviously to think about the
role that, at least in the תורה's Torah conception, part of that
issue is the status that the woman has as a בתולה betulah
or not, and so how vaginal sex influences that is different than
the way the רבנים Rabbanim understand anal sex, because only the husband
makes her בעולה be'ulah through an act of anal sex. And so
this תוספות רי"ד הזקן Tosafot Rid HaZaken addresses that question, and he
tries to explain the רמב"ם Rambam שיטה shita a little bit to
try to fit it back into the other גמרות Gemaras in כתובות.
Ketubot. And just to take a look also in the תוספות, Tosafot,
the four different שיטות shitos that I didn't get to explain earlier.
Four different שיטות shitos how תוספות Tosafot meshes this גמרא, Gemara, which
says, like אמימר Amemar says the end of the גמרא, Gemara, אמימר
משמיה דרבא כל הבועל דעתו על גמר ביאה. Amemar mishmeih deRava kol
habo'el da'ato al g'mar bi'ah. That is, when a man is having
sex, his intent is to the completion of the sexual act, while
in יבמות Yevamot it sounds like העראה, ha'ara'ah, the initial penetration, is
what counts as a sexual act. So here the four different explanations
in תוספות. Tosafot. So אומר רשב"א, omer Rashba, that's the רשב"א משאנץ.
Rashba mi-Shantz. דכי אמרינן העראה קונה היינו
בשלא עשה כי
אם העראה.
dechi amrinan ha'ara'ah kona haynu beshelo asa
ki im ha'ara'ah. So when we say העראה ha'ara'ah works, that's because
you only did העראה. ha'ara'ah. But if the process was completed, then
the דעת da'at kicks in only at the final stage of the
sexual act. That's the רשב"א's Rashba position. Then if you go down
a little bit further, והריב"ם תירץ דהתם דנקנה בהעראה היינו מפרש שרוצה
לקנות בהעראה. vehaRibam tiratz dehatam denikna beha'ara'ah haynu mefaresh sherotze liknot beha'ara'ah.
You get your choice. The husband's דעת da'at is dependent on which
part of the sexual act his intent is on. If he's thinking
about the first act, then that would count. And if he's waiting
until the end, then that is what would count. ורבינו תם תירץ
דאחרי שנמצא. veRabbeinu Tam tiratz de'acharei shenimtza. דאחרי שנתרבת העראה כגמר ביאה
d'acharei shenitrabat ha'ara k'gmar bi'ah once the תלמוד Talmud in יבמות Yevamos
had included penetration as the sexual act, what does רבינו תם Rabbeinu
Tam say in this important distinction? כל מקום שמזכיר ביאה בהעראה, kol
makom she'mazkir bi'ah b'ha'ara, every place that sex is mentioned refers to
the initial penetration, והכי קאמר תחילת העראה קונה או סוף העראה. ve-hachi
ka'amar techilat ha'ara kona o sof ha'ara. When the גמרא Gemara is
talking about the beginning or the end of the sexual act is
not actually talking about the beginning or the end of the sexual
act. Is it the beginning of the beginning or is it the
end of the beginning as we would say? So that's the question,
that's רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, and רב ניסים גאון Rav Nissim Gaon
who was from North Africa and was not a גאון, Gaon, רבינו
ניסים גאון Rabbeinu Nissim Gaon תירץ teireitz דההיא ביבמות איירי אחר קידושין
דעל ידי אותה העראה הוי כנשואה כמו חופה. d'hahi b'Yevamos ayri achar
kiddushin d'al yedei ota ha'ara havi k'nesua k'mo chuppah. So he distinguishes
between which sexual act can create חופה, that is in יבום yibbum
we have a lower standard because we say the יבמה yevama is
already זקוקה ועומדת. zekuka ve-omedet. The role, the legal role that this
action is taking is a lower weight legal action compared to in
this case קידושין trying to do more so the דעת da'at is
on גמר ביאה. gmar bi'ah.
So about your child
abuse thing, the child abuse thing, I don't remember exactly the line
in תוספות Tosafos I have to go back and check maybe I
can mention it to you tomorrow.
I was trying to do תוספות Tosafos's discussion about how the age
of three maybe but maybe I'll turn off the recorder and we
can take a look for a few minutes and then and then.